Hello everyone and welcome back to another lesson here at
English pod my name is Marco and my name is Catherine so Marco
what are we talking about today today we are taking a look
at a guy who is a little bit too afraid of people in general
there's a good word for this in
English someone who's almost too afraid
all the time someone who is overly
cautious we call this person paranoid
okay so if you are paranoid
you think that everyone is
uh wants to hurt you or
that everyone is out to get it
wait did you hear that that's
not it did you hear that I didn't
some of the door and said
Marco can you can you check that
okay that's paranoid you know
you always hearing voices and
noises and things so a paranoid
somebody that is paranoid
all right so why don't we
listen to this dialogue for the
first time and see what this
person is all paranoid about
there it's again
Dan Dan dude you have
to come over to my house
right now is everything
okay just get over here
come in quickly so since when
is your house a bank what do
you mean I mean what's up
with the four locks and iron bars
on your windows security Dan
security you can never be too
safe you know a lot of sickos
out there just the other day they
cut that keeping Tom red hand
had a high-power counsel binoculars
by his window what's the matter
with you why are you acting
all paranoid paranoid
I'm not paranoid I'm
cautious you see then we
have to be on guard in all
time people just invade
your privacy as if they knew
you tell marketers solicitors
even your bank they
they have way too much
information I like to keep
everything on need to know
bases okay well what did you
want to see me about you're being
watched be careful then be careful
all right we're back so
yeah I think this guy is
a little bit too cautious
I would have to agree
with you and I would go
so far as to call him paranoid
but there's a lot of great
stuff in this dialogue that we
can use in a lot of different
situations so let's take
a look at some of these new
words in today's language
takeaway language takeaway
all right the first word on
language takeaway today is
sicko sicko is also the name
of a movie that was a
documentary famous in America
by Michael Moore actually
but sicko in this context
means someone who is a
bit weird in a bad way so if you
tell somebody you're sick
but like in that tone right you're
saying you're sick you're
a sick person you're gross
right you're saying you're
gross or in a pro people who
have inappropriate humor
who make jokes about
not so nice things right
yeah they're sick but in
this case sickos are
people who maybe like to
hurt other people or
people who are a little bit
crazy people who are
not normal so it's not a
nice way of calling
someone crazy right if you say
oh he's a sicko it's not
really nice not at all it's a
way of saying that you're
almost scared of this person
because they're kind of
weird and almost they have
problems all right so sicko
moving on to our next word we
saw that the guy was afraid
of telemarketers exactly so what
are these guys well we've got
two words being put together
here tele and market so
tele like telephone telephone
community over communication
so they're not in person
they're people who call you
up and market things they try
to sell you stuff over the
phone so this is very common
you're you get a phone call
on your cell phone and they
ask you if you're if you're
happy with your long distance
calling plan or if you need
new TV cable or something like
that and they always call
during dinner or late at night
which drives me nuts exactly
so these are telemarketers
these are people who call
you trying to sell things to you
and a very similar to to
these is a solicitors exactly but
the big difference here with
solicitors and telemarketers
is that solicitors actually go
to your house they knock on
your door so they're also
called a door to door salesman
or salesman that's right so
door to door salesman they go
from door to door trying to
sell things but in this case a
solicitor is someone who
comes to your house to try to get
you to do something to buy
something alright very good and
moving on to our next word
we have a peeping Tom that's
right we heard this a little
bit earlier in the dialogue
and a peeping Tom is
again a negative thing to say
about someone a peeping
Tom will the word "peep" means
to look but kind of like
yeah it's a quick look so
peeping Tom is a person
who spies on other people
okay so a synonym of a peeping Tom
would be a voyeur a voyeur so someone who
without getting caught tries to look at
other people while they're in their homes
and so it's really bad because
it's usually inappropriate
it's usually people who are
watching women get undressed
so a peeping Tom is just
an informal way of saying
a voyeur or somebody
who is spying on people
so those are the words for
today in language take away let's
listen to our dialogue again
and then we'll be right back
then then dude you have to
come over to my house right
now is everything okay just
get over here come in quickly
so since when is your house a
bank what do you mean I mean
what's up with the four locks
and iron bars on your windows
security Dan security you can
never be too safe you know a lot of
sickos out there just the other day
they cut that peeping Tom red handed
had a high power telescope
and binoculars by his window
what's the matter with you
why are you acting all paranoid
paranoid I'm not paranoid I'm
cautious you see Dan we have to be on
guard at all time people just invade
your privacy as if they knew you
telemarketers solicitors even
your bank they have way too much
information I like to keep
everything on a need to know basis
okay well what did you
want to see me about you're
being watched be careful
then be careful now we're back
and we had some interesting
phrases in the dialogue
the first one being you
can never be too safe
fluency builder alright
so this is this is a common
mom phrase you often
hear mothers say this when
they're sending their kids
off to school or whatever they
don't talk to strangers and
the kid says oh why not you can
never be too safe all
right it's it's good to air on
the side of caution so
it's okay to be extra extra
safe or extra cautious just in
case exactly you never know
what's going to happen so it's
better to be cautious than not
and that's what this person's
saying he's saying well
security it's important you
can never be too safe you never
know what might happen
is there another way that
we can combine it like
you can never be too careful
exactly basically the same
same same thing yeah alright
what's our next phrase
our next phrase is about this
peeping Tom this person that
they caught they caught him
red-handed we caught you red-handed
or he's been caught red-handed
so what does that mean
it's a big colorful phrase and I
don't just mean that because
we're calling him red-handed
but to catch red-handed means
to catch someone while they're
doing something wrong so I see
you breaking into someone's house
and I say Marco stop I'm
catching you stop now I just
caught you red-handed I
saw me doing the act exactly
in another way of saying
this is you caught him with his
hand in the cookie jar okay
and this is this is another great
phrase you can imagine a
child who sees the cookies in
a very special jar on the
counter in the kitchen and
mom says donate the cookies
well the child goes into the kitchen
and sees the cookies and opens
the jar and puts his hand in the jar
and then mom comes and says
caught you that's that's the boy
with his hand or a child with
their hand in the cookie jar
so it's the same thing I can
say I caught you with your
hand in the cookie jar or
you are caught red-handed
all right and our last
phrase for today is you are
on a need to know basis
all right this is a great one
this is often said in spy movies
I think so say you're gonna need
to know basis that means that if
you really need to know something
then I will tell you right
but if not I won't so you
only have the information
that is necessary no more
or less right you're on a
need to know basis right so I
say tell me Marco tell me
what happened I want to know
all right and I can say
no no you're on a need to
know basis and you don't
need to know all right so
a need to know basis as
you say very popular among
spy movies and government
movies and stuff like that
conspiracy movies yeah
all right so let's listen to this
dialogue for the very last
time and we'll be right back
so then then dude you have
to come over to my house
right now is everything
okay just get over here
come in quickly so since
when is your house of bank what
do you mean I mean what's
up with the four locks and
iron bars on your windows
security Dan security
you can never be too
safe you know a lot of
sickos up there just the
other day they caught
that keeping Tom red hand
had a high power council
and binoculars by his
window what's the matter
with you why are you
acting all paranoid paranoid
I'm not paranoid I'm cautious you see then
we have to be on guard in all time people
just invade your privacy as if
they knew you telemarketers
solicitors even your bank they
have way too much information
I like to keep everything
on a need to know basis okay
well what did you want to
see me about you're being
watched be careful then
all right so the guys a
little bit paranoid there's
another word for this as
well similar right let's
get so schizophrenia is
a disease and a lot of
people have it and it's
not too uncommon but a
popular slang word to say
someone's crazy is get so
so if you guys remember this
movie a beautiful mind
it's all about this famous
mathematician named John
Nash and well he was a genius
he came up with game
theory and a lot of subsequent
usage of this for economy
for many things but it was
proven that he was
schizophrenic right a paranoid
schizophrenic so not only
did he kind of have experience
reality in different ways
but he's also paranoid so
he was afraid that the
government was trying to kill
him and so he was he
was irrationally afraid of
everything going on
around him and it made him
very unsafe because he
could hurt himself or her
other people and the
interesting thing about this is
that there is no actual
cure for it you just
learn to cope and live
with it so you never really
get cured you just kind
of learn how to understand
what's real and what's
not so it's interesting it's
a great movie also by the
way if you ever if you've
never seen it or you get
a chance to watch it and
that's all the time we have
for today so if you have
any questions doubts or
comments please come to our
website english pop dot
com and we're there to answer
them yeah we hope to see
you there and until next time
English potties all right bye bye